Today’s דף daf is ל״ט, Lamed Tet, and we start a new
פרק. perek. Thank you to everybody who covered for me when I
was gone.
And yeah, let’s talk about where we’re up to. As you’ve been
seeing, the משניות mishnayot do a lot of pulling in and pulling
out in terms of giving framework about how to proceed during the
normal,
during the rest of the year. We talked about the whole issue
about the lots that were drawn to distribute the various עבודות. avodot.
Then we talked about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol going to the
מקוה. mikvah. Then we pulled back to discuss how anybody who went
into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash would go to the מקוה. mikvah.
Then we talked about the drawing of the lots, the drawing of
the lots from the box and about
how those were made special. The משנה mishnah says,
language of the משנה mishnah is, where was it?
That actually the lot was of אשכרוע, eshkora,
which I think is some type of a wood. And then it
says ובן גמלא עשה של זהב, u'Ben Gamla asah shel zahav, Ben
Gamla made them out of זהב, zahav, gold. And then that led
to this larger discussion about other people that made special things for
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and some people that withheld some of
their talents from contributing to them in a larger way to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So again, it’s interesting the way we’ve been
pulling in and going into the עבודה avoda and then pulling back,
going in and going back. But we are getting more and more
into the regular discussion of the עבודה avoda and there will be
much less, if any, pulling back now that we’re really going to
be hitting the stride and talking about how the עבודה avoda went
forward. And we start that with our new פרק perek of טרף
בקלפי. Tarof B'Kalfi. So let’s take a look. So also one thing
to remind you, and again now some of them are here, thank
you again for everybody who helped when I was gone. One thing
to remind you, can I now erase this diagram? Yes, you may.
This diagram becomes obsolete now. Okay, so I know it was very
complicated, some of the debates between אביי Abaye and others of exactly
the order of some of the things in the morning, but let’s
try to just generally remind ourselves
of what was going on.
Okay, that will be
easy. אולם, Ulam, היכל, Heichal, those are covered. Okay. So
מנורה, Menorah, שלחן, Shulchan,
מזבח הזהב, Mizbe'ach HaZahav, קדש הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. Okay.
And right, this is everything else, right?
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, whatever, okay. So
what have we said so far has happened? We start by the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol שוחט shochets the תמיד. Tamid. Okay, so here's
the תמיד. Tamid. Okay. He שוחט shochets the תמיד Tamid
and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol שוחט shochets the תמיד Tamid and
then he catches the דם. dam. Then he goes in and he
does זריקה zrika of the דם dam on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And
then he goes in and he takes care of cleaning the מנורה,
menorah, burning the
קטרת, ketoret, finishing up with the מנורה. menorah. Coming out, he puts
the אברים evarim on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, and he's done with the
תמיד. Tamid. That
was the first stuff that gets done every day is the bringing
of the תמיד, Tamid, the taking care of the קטרת ketoret and
the מנורה, menorah, and the putting the אברים evarim on the כבש.
kevesh. Okay. So that was what he did with בגדי זהב. bigdei
zahav. Then we said that he's now going to switch into, so
that's stage number one. There are going to be five switches of
clothes, so three בגדי זהב, bigdei zahav, two in בגדי לבן. bigdei
lavan. Now up to stage two with בגדי לבן. bigdei lavan. Where
did it say that he stood? Anybody remember when he comes to
his פר? par? Where's the פר par standing? It's facing,
the head is towards the
west. It's standing facing south, its
head is towards the west. Okay, he stands here and you never
ever erase this.
You like my amazing artistic ability? Yes.
Okay, so anyway,
and he does the
וידוי, viduy, and that he's doing with בגדי לבן. bigdei lavan. And
then it says, now we're up to our stage, he comes to
the drawing of the lots.
So what does the משנה mishnah say? מה? Mah? No.
So
it says, בא לו למזרח עזרה לצפון המזבח. Ba lo l'mizrach azara
l'tzfon ha'mizbe'ach. Okay, מזרח עזרה, לצפון המזבח. mizrach azara letzfon hamizbeach,
So he's coming back here, the north of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the
east side of the עזרה. azara. Okay, so here now. Okay, מזרח
עזרה mizrach azara,
לצפון המזבח, l'tzfon ha'mizbe'ach. so he's coming back here. What? He's coming
back here. The north of the מזבח, mizbeach, the east side of
the עזרה. azara. Okay, so here now the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
he's done with his פר, par, he returns to being over here,
okay, and now he is going to be doing the drawing of
the lots with the two שעירים, se'irim,
okay, and the drawing up of the lot. Okay, and that's where
we're up to now. He's still in בגדי לבן, bigdei lavan, he
did his פר, par, and he's going here to start with the
שעירים. se'irim. So let's take a look.
Yeah I know, I can't... I'm sorry if I cannot draw goats.
Should I make horns on it?
I'll make horns. Okay. And they're white goats.
All right, so that's where we're up to. Let's
take... yeah, oh stop it already. All right, so let's take a
look. All right, so now we start with our פרק perek and
he's about to draw the lot.
So okay, let's take a look.
טרף בקלפי. tarof bikalfi. So he, she, you know, mixed around in
the box that held the lot. והעלה שני גורלות vehe'ela shenei goralot
and he drew out two lots. אחד כתוב עליו לה' ואחד כתוב
עליו לעזאזל. echad katuv alav lashem ve'echad katuv alav la'azazel. One says
for God and one says לעזאזל, la'azazel, which we won't translate for
now, but עזאזל. Azazel. Okay, so הסגן מימינו וראש בית אב משמאלו.
hasgan mimino verosh beit av mismolo. So there was two people with
him as he was doing this. The סגן, sgan, the assistant כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, the sort of vice כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, who
basically didn't do anything, he was sort of like the vice president,
you know, his only job was to be there if the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol died, okay, but this was one of the few
sort of tasks he did, but generally his role did not have
that much significance.
But you said that last משנה, mishna, right? You said הסגן מימינו.
hasgan mimino.
Yeah I know, we're repeating, we're going back because we digressed. Yeah,
okay. וראש בית אב משמאלו, verosh beit av mismolo, the head of
the בית אב, beit av, which is the family whose day יום
כיפור Yom Kippur fell out on, right? Because you have a משמר
mishmar that works for the week, divided into
days for each family per day, is on his left. And so
that obviously is a less significant position than the סגן, sgan, who
is like the more regular vice כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. This one
just has significance this one day.
Now, אם עלה שם על בימינו, im ala shem al biyamino, if
the lot that had God's name came in his right hand, and
that was considered to be a good סימן, siman, because you know
right is always preferred, so הסגן אומר לו, hasgan omer lo, so
the סגן sgan who is standing on his right says אישי כהן
גדול, ishi Kohen Gadol, Mr. כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, הגבה ימינך, hagebe
yeminkha, lift up your right hand, as a way of signifying that
that was the one that had God's name on it. ואם עלה
שם על בשמאלו, ve'im ala shem al bismolo, if it came in
his left hand,
ראש בית אב אומר לו, rosh beit av omer lo, אישי כהן
גדול, ishi Kohen Gadol, Mr. כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, הגבה שמאלך, hagebe
smolkha, lift up your left hand. נתנן על שני השעירים, natanan al
shenei hase'irim, which one had God's name in it. נתנן על
שני השעירים, natanan al shenei hase'irim, now after sort of the goats
are standing in front of him, he sort of picks out right
and left, they're sort of
already opposite the goats that they represent. But you lift up the
one of שם, shem, which is seen as obviously the one of
more significance, and now you're going to actually place the lots on
top of the goats. That's based on the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק
pasuk says ונתן על שני השעירים גורלות. venatan al shenei hase'irim goralot.
So literally put it on top of them. נתנן על שני השעירים
natanan al shenei hase'irim ואומר לה' חטאת ve'omer lashem chatat and he
says for the one that has God's name on it, he says
לה' חטאת. lashem chatat. He does not explicitly... yes, we will... and
what was I going to say? He does not explicitly label the
one of לעזאזל, la'azazel, that's sort of inferred. רבי
ישמעאל אומר לא היה צריך לומר חטאת אלא לה'. Rabbi Yishmael omer
lo haya tzarikh lomar chatat ela lashem. Right? לה' lashem because that's
the לשון lashon of the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk is גורל
אחד לה'
וגורל אחד לעזאזל,
goral echad lashem vegoral
echad
la'azazel, you know, אשר
עלה עליו הגורל לה' ועשהו חטאת. asher ala alav hagoral lashem ve'asahu
chatat. But it's לה', lashem, and לה' lashem is certainly more in
contrast to the לעזאזל. la'azazel. To where is it going, not necessarily
what type of קרבן korban it is, but is it לה' lashem
or is it לעזאזל. la'azazel.
והן עונים אחריו ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד vehen onim acharav
barukh shem kevod malkhuto le'olam va'ed and they heard God's explicit שם
shem and they would say ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד. barukh
shem kevod malkhuto le'olam va'ed. I want to just make two comments
about this before we continue, besides the much larger עזאזל Azazel comment
which we can discuss a little bit later. But number one is
the idea that we tend to focus, you know, on the basic
כפרה kappara of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Like the major עבודה avoda
as we're going to be focusing on as we learn this, and
you know, the whole thing about פשעתי עויתי pashati aviti and everybody
bows down, you know, אחת אחת ואחת, akhat akhat ve'akhat, all of
that in the תורה Torah is around cleansing the מקדש. mikdash. The
idea of atoning for our sins, you know, is basically the שעיר
לעזאזל, se'ir la'azazel, ונשא עליו את כל עונותם אל ארץ גזירה. venasa
alav et kol avonotam el eretz gezeira. Now it is true that
there's a connection of cleansing the מקדש mikdash and cleansing the sins.
The end of the פסוקים pesukim say, what's the פסוק pasuk say?
וכפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל ומפשעיהם לכל חטאתם. vekhiper al hakodesh
mitumot benei Yisrael umipisheihem lekhol chatatam. So the cleansing of the מקדש
mikdash is a cleansing not only of ritual impurity but somehow of
the way the sins have sullied the מקדש, mikdash, and that's a
very important idea in general that חטאת... chatat... חטאת Chatat does not
necessarily mean sin offering, it could mean cleansing, and that's why it's
brought, you know, after somebody finishes a, like a woman who's a
יולדת Yoledet or a זב Zav at the end of that process
of purification. And the idea in the תורה, Torah, it's important to
to note this, is that, you know, that basically, when you sin,
the metaphysical effect of sin is that it dirties up the מקדש
Mikdash in a metaphysical way. It like creates, you know, stains the
מקדש. Mikdash. And therefore, יום כיפור Yom Kippur in a way is
the once a year cleaning crew that goes in, the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, and you know, cleanses, gets all the gunk out, all
of the ways in which it's been metaphysical gunk, right, in which
it's been impurified. And if you read the פסוקים Pesukim in the
תורה, Torah, you will find that the focus in the תורה Torah
on the שעיר להשם Seir L'Hashem and the פר החטאת Par HaChatat
of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is to cleanse the מקדש. Mikdash.
It's to cleanse the way the מקדש. Mikdash. Now, of course, that
what that means is, if the מקדש Mikdash is being sullied, then
God is not able to remain among בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. ושכנתי
בתוכם, V'shachanti betocham, right? השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם. Hashochen itam betoch tumatam.
God is willing to to, you know, tolerate the טומאה Tumah to
a certain degree and continue to dwell among us בתוך טומאתם. betoch
tumatam. But we have to cleanse that טומאה Tumah on a yearly
basis to allow God to continue to dwell among us. So it's
important, you know, to a, appreciate sort of the whole metaphysical universe
in which this is inhabiting, which is not normally the way we
think. We think very much about our own personal sins, being cleansed
from our personal sins, you know, and so on. And whereas really
this has a much more national focus, God's presence among the nation,
the way sin, you know, injures the environment, sullies the environment, and
that this allows God to remain within us as a nation. So
that's the real focus. The שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel is much more
about like taking care of your personal sins, not about the cleansing
of the מקדש. Mikdash. So it's worth pointing out, you know, that
in as we're going to read this, the להשם L'Hashem becomes, that's
the חשוב Chashuv one. לעזאזל L'Azazel we don't even really like want
to talk about that like, you know, the big issue is that
your right hand should have להשם, L'Hashem, you call out להשם, L'Hashem,
you don't say לעזאזל, L'Azazel, you know, and that sort of becomes
very much the focus. But the thing that, you know, tends to
speak to our idea of יום כיפור Yom Kippur as opposed to
the sort of תורה Torah idea, you know, of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is is much more the role that the שעיר לעזאזל Seir
L'Azazel plays. So it's worth keeping keeping that in mind, as we
continue to learn this and learn how, you know, what's the emphasis
on the importance of the one that's להשם חטאת. L'Hashem Chatat.
Yeah, there was thinking about Jacob Milgrom who was a a professor
of Bible at Berkeley for decades.
His formulation is that the blood is the metaphysical agent, it's the
detergent. Right.
I forgot that part of it. Right. He talks about, right, that
removes טומאה.
Tumah. So it's very powerful because the blood is the life. Uh-huh.
The live blood is the...
Right, I forgot that quality of the blood as the cleanser, as
the detergent.
But yes, so the emphasis here is totally going to be on
his פר, Par, on the שעיר לחטאת, Seir LaChatat, you know, we'll
get to the עזאזל, Azazel, you know, but again, I'm just speaking
personally, I think for us, for me, the focus was always, oh,
the one לעזאזל, L'Azazel, that's what, who, what's he doing in the
מקדש? Mikdash? What does that... I mean, it's very nice to go
through the whole process, but what really matters is you send the
שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel off the cliff and the red string becomes
white and you know that you're atoned for and that's what we're
really paying attention to. But you know, that's not the way it
is in the תורה Torah and that's not obviously the emphasis here,
which is on the שעיר לחטאת. Seir LaChatat.
Yeah, it's interesting, just because you mentioned it, a lot of phrases
from from this משנה Mishnah became common English expressions. Like what?
Scapegoat. Oh, well that's not the משנה, Mishnah, scapegoat is based on
the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel in the תורה. Torah. Yes, that's totally
true. Right, exactly.
But it is interesting that you mentioned that and the goat to
עזאזל. Azazel.
Oh, if you translate עזאזל Azazel as hell, it's go in
there, it's go to עזאזל. Azazel.
Right, I mean, whether עזאזל Azazel in contrast to להשם L'Hashem means
some idea of a demon or what exactly it means, maybe we'll
talk about that a little bit later. I want to say one
other thing here though about the drawing of the lots, which is
that if you think about it, right, the whole idea of drawing
of lots is quite strange. I mean, the תורה Torah talks about
it,
but it sort of makes it like it's almost random, what goes
להשם L'Hashem and what goes לעזאזל. L'Azazel. You know, and if you
would think about something like יום כיפור Yom Kippur is about, I
mean again talking about it in our terms of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, about sort of owning our responsibility and doing תשובה, Teshuvah, it's
about not sort of blaming things on forces beyond your control. It's
like taking ownership and responsibility about your choice and your freedom of
choice. So what's the significance of the lots? And there's a lot
been written, and there's plenty that has been written on it. But
I also want to point out that it connects to an earlier
theme, like I talked, you know, which is the theme of what
was, we had a whole discussion of lots on a daily basis,
about which כהן Kohen gets to do which service, right? And that
seems like a whole digression. There's been things that sort of have
been pulling back and talking about larger things of what happens on
a daily basis. But it is worth thinking about the centrality in
the מקדש Mikdash on a daily basis and for this sort of
like very high high-focused
עבודה avodah that gets done on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the sense
of luck and lots and what's that supposed to be sort of
signifying. So I raise it as a question, not that I have
a profound answer. Somebody told me that somebody they know actually did
a whole dissertation on the idea of lots in the מקדש Mikdash
and sort of lot, you know, sort of, so I have to
find,
anyway, I'm going to find the dissertation. But a lot of it
is exactly about this idea of the daily גורל goral and the
גורל goral that was done on יום עזאזל. Yom Azazel. What sort
of significance that has in terms of the meaning of what goes
on in the מקדש. Mikdash.
I think that lots were what we associate with them as being
an indication of random luck, but like in the book of יונה.
Yonah.
More like סיעתא דשמיא, Siyata Dishmaya, the opposite.
Exactly. In other words, the way the גורל goral falls out is
actually a
reflection of...
right, right. I'm not sure we got a hint of that in
terms of the daily one of the כהנים. Kohanim.
And also even if that's true, so I'm not exactly sure what
the direct connection is to the עבודה יום כיפור avodah Yom Kippur
to be sort of
underscoring. It's always an important religious message, God's presence in our lives,
God's guiding hand, but exactly how that plays out in the significance
of this. It's certainly worth thinking about. I'll try, I'm going to
try to find that dissertation and try to address it more as
we continue. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. למה איטרף
בקלפי? Lama itraf be-kylpi? Why do you have to, you know, mix
them up? Just pick one. What's the idea of like shaking up
the box? Or it might actually mean not only his hand mixes
them up, but like you shake up the box before he drives.
Well, exactly. כי היכי דלא נכוין ולישקול, Ki heichi delo nechavein velishkol,
so he shouldn't sort of intentionally try to draw out the one
that says להשם La-Hashem in his right hand. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
קלפי של עץ הייתה ושל חול הייתה. Kylpi shel etz hayeta veshel
chol hayeta. The box was actually, although we talked about the lots
being made of gold, the box actually was made out of wood
and it was not sanctified. ואינה מחזקת אלא שתי ידים, Ve-eina machazeket
ela shtei yadayim, and only two hands could fit into it. מתקיף
לה רבינא. Matkif la Ravina. So Ravina said, בשלמא אינה מחזקת אלא
שתי ידים, Beshalma eina machazeket ela shtei yadayim, I understand why it
only had the space for two hands. כי היכי דלא נכוין ולישקול,
Ki heichi delo nechavein velishkol, because the more space you have, right,
the more you'll be able to like feel, especially if it's like
in, you know, if it's carved, the name is into it, you
know, but you can sort of feel the lot that you're picking
up and feel the writing. But if it's very tight space, you
can just stick your hand in and pull it out, you don't
have the ability to feel that. Also, I should say we're going
to see another approach, another idea, that the סגן Sgan took one
lot and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol took the other lot. So
then you certainly need room for two hands. Okay. אלא של חול,
Ela shel chol, but why was it not, why was it
unsanctified? נקדשה, Nikadshe, let's sanctify it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no.
אם כן הוה ליה כלי שרת, Im ken havei lei kli sharet,
then it will become a כלי שרת. kli sharet. של עץ, Shel
etz, out of wood. וכלי שרת דעץ לא עבדינן, Ukli sharet d'etz
lo avidnan, and we don't make כלי שרת kli sharet out of
עץ, etz, out of wood. Not appropriate. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ונעבדיה דכסף ונעבדיה דזהב, Venaavdei dechesef venaavdei dezahav, okay, so make
it sanctified and make it out of gold or silver. No. התורה
חסה על ממונם של ישראל, HaTorah chasa al mamonam shel Yisrael, God
is concerned, the Torah is concerned for us not to waste our
money. And we learn that out because by the מצורע, Metzora, it
says he clears out the house before he has the כהן Kohen
inspect the house. And חז"ל Chazal say why? I mean, even if
all the vessels are טמא, tamei, just take them to the מקווה.
Mikvah. So what's the big deal? So no, he has to clear
out the house because of the pottery vessels that they, if they're
found טמא, tamei, there's no way of making them טהור. tahor. So
says look how much the Torah goes out of its way to
help this מצורע Metzora who normally is assumed to be, you know,
to have done something to deserve his status, and to help him
protect his pottery vessels. So clearly the Torah is concerned even that
we shouldn't waste even pennies and is concerned for even small amounts
of money for our money. Now, of course, the funny thing is,
here you have a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash where everything is out
of gold and silver.
All of a sudden, this is the one thing? And we just
had the משנה Mishna that said what, the כהן גדול's, Kohen Gadol
you know, garments, the white ones, and they're twelve מנה, maneh, eighteen
מנה, maneh, we're spending all this money, and all of a sudden
התורה חסה על ממונם של ישראל? HaTorah chasa al mamonam shel Yisrael?
Like, I really, I'm open for explanations. I don't know.
They made the lots, right, not the box?
Just the lots and that's also the irony, the lots are gold
and the box is זהב... zahav... so... you know again I really
really don't get it. Maybe if we can get better insight into
the whole significance of the lots, we can get insight into why
you want it to be a wooden box.
But as for the פשט, p'shat, as Rashi says, פשט p'shat from
the Torah, that's private money and this is public money, what
do you think is different? Right, that's also a good point, right,
public funds, square good point. Yeah, I mean, considering how many things
they spent
money on to have one more little gold box, okay, I don't
know. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא,
Matnitin d'lo k'hai tanna, our משנה Mishna is not like the following
תנא, tanna, דתניא, detanya, as it was taught in a ברייתא. Braisa.
רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer,
הסגן וכהן גדול מכניסין ידיהן בקלפי. HaSgan veKohen Gadol machnisin yadeihen be-kylpi.
That actually Rabbi Yehuda says in the name of Rabbi Eliezer that
it wasn't the כהן Kohen took one in his right and one
in his left, but actually the סגן Sgan and the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol each took, each stuck their right hand in and each
one took one lot. And it would still be more significant that
it was in the right hand of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
rather than the right hand of the סגן. Sgan. אם בימינו של
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol? עולה *Im biyemino shel Kohen Gadol olah*, if
it came up in the right hand of the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, *Kohen Gadol*, הסגן אומר לו איש כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, הגבה
ימינך *Hasgan omer lo ish Kohen Gadol hagbei yemincha*, so the סגן
sgan *sgan* would say, Mr. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*, raise
up your right hand. ואם בימינו של סגן sgan עולה *Ve’im biyemino
shel sgan olah*, and if it was in the right hand of
the סגן sgan *sgan*, then ראש בית אב אומר לו לכהן גדול
דבר מילך *Rosh beit av omer lo l’Kohen Gadol dvar milcha*. Then
the ראש בית אב *Rosh beit av* does not say to the
סגן sgan *sgan* raise up your right hand because that would you
know be sort of you know not seen as disrespectful to the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*. So so what would he do?
So the ראש בית אב *Rosh beit av* would say to the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol* say your words, meaning say the
words like להשם חטאת L'Hashem chatat. *L’Hashem chatat* on the one in
which it’s opposite. So he would he would still be the one
designating the animal as the חטאת *chatat* even though it was the
סגן sgan *sgan* that actually took out the took out the thing.
Now I need to stop and say something about this because we’re
going to have a whole discussion in a little while about whether
בדיעבד *bedi’avad* this is מעכב meakev, *me’akev* or not, the drawing of
the lots. Can you just say להשם L'Hashem חטאת *L’Hashem chatat* without
drawing the lots? Is the drawing of the lots מעכב meakev. *me’akev*?
There’s going to be a debate. But and one of the רש"י'ס
*Rashi’s* there says something. It’s actually put in parentheses so it might
have been a later gloss but says something that you know was
bothering me all along which is how can this be working here?
In in the according to the first version he takes one thing
in his right and one thing in his left. But עבודה avoda,
*avodah* is פסול בשמאל *pasul b’smol*. Okay? So the according to the
other version fine, you use his right hand and the right hand
of the סגן sgan *sgan*. But on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom
Kippur* all the עבודות *avodot* have to be done by the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol*. So here you’re having so if you’re
getting עבודה avoda. בשמאל *avodah b’smol* or you’re getting עבודה avoda. *avodah*
not the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol*. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says you even if this is מעכב meakev? *me’akev* you have to
say that it is not being identified as an עבודה avoda, *avodah*,
which raises you know interesting questions. What exactly do you label an
עבודה avoda, *avodah*? Only things that are regularly done during the year,
you know זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* and so on? But this can
be is this is something that must be done on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*, but it’s not an עבודה avoda *avodah* and therefore בדיעבד
*bedi’avad* can be done or not בדיעבד *bedi’avad*, it can be done
either with the left hand of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen
Gadol* or with partly participating a non-כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol*.
So that’s one thing to realize. So and that also could explain
maybe why there’s two opinions: which is better, the left of the
כהן kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol* or the סגן sgan. *sgan*? Yes.
But if it’s not an עבודה avoda,
*avodah*,
how can it be
מעכב meakev, *me’akev* be relevant?
Right, so then it becomes a funny idea that something which is
not labeled as an עבודה *avodah*, you know, could be מעכב meakev.
*me’akev*. Look, שחיטה *shechitah* is שחיטה כשרה בזר *shechitah kshairah b’zar*. Is
that an עבודה *avodah* that’s כשרה בזר *kshairah b’zar* or not an
עבודה *avodah*? You know, so exactly what we label an עבודה *avodah*
becomes a you know a real question. There’s a whole issue whether
the שחיטה *shechitah* of the of the פר *par* can be done
with a non-כהן kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol* because maybe it is not
an עבודה *avodah* even though it is obviously a necessary part of
what’s happening. So it becomes an interesting question of the difference between
מעכב *me’akev* and what you label an עבודה *avodah*.
It’s a הכשר עבודה *hechsher avodah*.
Yeah, that’s the way it would be understood.
Now, would you call this a כלי שרת *kli sharet*? Right? I
mean this קלפי *kalfi*, the only thing it had was these two
lots. So it was only used in
the in the context of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit Hamikdash*, right?
But nevertheless not a כלי שרת *kli sharet*? If you don’t sanctify
it, it doesn’t become a כלי שרת *kli sharet*. But they perform
as if it is, right? Right, right. So there are those differences
between the function and its identity clearly. So okay so according to
this, right, if it’s the כהן Kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol* and he
has a right and a left, still you’re going to whether it’s
right or left you’re going to say the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
lift up the hand because the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* will then
be the one raising the hand over the one that’s להשם L'Hashem
*L’Hashem*. But if it’s the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* and the סגן
sgan. *sgan* and the סגן *sgan* has the one that says להשם
חטאת *L’Hashem chatat*, then you don’t want to give the סגן *sgan*
the role of saying להשם *L’Hashem* onto the onto the פר *par*.
And that role you’re going to give to the כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol*. So therefore if the סגן *sgan* has it, the ראש בית
אב *rosh beit av* says to the כהן *kohen*, say your line,
דבר מילך *dvar milcha*. And then the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* says
to the one he so he gets what that means and he
says to the one that’s opposite the סגן *sgan*, להשם חטאת *L’Hashem
chatat*. And the reason so the reason I took a step back
here to talk about the question of whether it’s an עבודה *avodah*
is so the drawing of the lots might be might not be
an עבודה *avodah* and therefore כשר *kasher* either with the left hand
or with the סגן *sgan*. But having saying the words להשם חטאת
*L’Hashem chatat*, okay? And we’re going to talk later that that might
ironically not be מעכב *me'akev* if you did the lots. So it’s
going to be ironic. But the saying of the words have to
be by the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. Because here you’re having the
סגן *sgan* do the lots but the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* well
that’s also true. Okay, but yeah that’s a good point too. He’s
doing the שם המפורש shem hamoforash. *shem hameforash*. Okay, so according to
this version the סגן *sgan*, if the סגן *sgan* drew it, then
he doesn’t say anything, the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* just says to
the one opposite the סגן *sgan*, להשם חטאת *L’Hashem chatat*. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
ונימליה סגן *Venimleih sgan*, why doesn’t the סגן *sgan* say to the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* say your words if the סגן *sgan* took
the one that said להשם *L’Hashem*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
no, כיון דלא סליק בידיה חלשא דעתיה *Keivan d’lo salik b’yadeih chalsha
da’ateih*. Since the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* did not get the one
that said להשם *L’Hashem*, the סגן *sgan* got it, so it’s like
rubbing it in for the סגן *sgan* to get the one to
say להשם *L’Hashem* and say now say your words. Then it’s like
the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* is like, you know, is like secondary
to the סגן *sgan*. So so you by so you
reorient, you get the ראש בית אב *rosh beit av* to say
so we sort of ignore the סגן *sgan*. You know, you get
that like if the סגן *sgan* got it and said to the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* say it, so the סגן *sgan* is now
the guy in charge and he’s telling the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* what to
do. If
the סגן *sgan* got it— Although it doesn't say that. It's a
good question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: במאי קמיפלגי?
B'mai kamifligi? What's the debate about whether it's the סגן or the
two hands of the כהן גדול? מר סבר ימינה דסגן עדיף משמאלא
דכהן גדול. Mar savar yemina de-sgan adif mismala de-Kohen Gadol. Better to
have a right hand of the סגן than the left hand of
the כהן גדול, presumably from the perspective of עבודה, but it's not
technically an עבודה. ומר סבר כי הדדי נינהו. U-mar savar ki hadadi
ninhu. They're equivalent and once they're more or less the same, it's
funny, they're equivalent and therefore we go with the כהן גדול, right?
I don't know why it didn't say the כהן גדול's better, but
I guess the point is once they're equivalent, why bring in another
person into the process?
Is right preferred ultimately because it's east?
Oh, I don't know. I mean, I don't think so. Yeah, I
hear that, but I don't think so. I always just assumed that,
you know, there's always in society been a bias towards right and
שמאל smol as more signify sinister and demonic and so on. I
don't think it's maybe that's connected, I don't know. So גמרא Gemara
says no, right isn't east, you're facing east. Right is always תימנה
Temana is always south. ימין Yamin and תימנה Temana is always south.
You face east, קדם Kedem is the way you face the rising
sun, so your right is תימנה Temana is your ימין Yamin is
south. So it's not east. בנימין, Binyamin, right? The northern brushes over
there is בנימין, Binyamin, right? That's okay. So anyways, the גמרא Gemara
says like this, okay. ומאן האי תנא דפליג עליה דרבי יהודה? U-man
hai tanna d'palig alei de-Rabbi Yehuda? Who is the תנא tanna that
argues on רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who is the author of our
משנה Mishnah that says it was the כהן גדול's two hands?
So the גמרא Gemara. says, רבי חנניא סגן הכהנים הוא. Rabbi Hanania
Sgan HaKohanim hu. Interesting.
So you actually have a סגן כהנים Sgan Kohanim being the author
of the opinion that the סגן wasn't involved in the drawing of
the lots. דתניא, Detanya, רבי חנניא סגן הכהנים אומר למה סגן מימינו?
Rabbi Hanania Sgan HaKohanim omer, lamma sgan mimino? Why is the סגן
on the right side? שאם אירע בו פסול בכהן גדול נכנס סגן
ומשמש תחתיו. She'im i'eir bo p'sul b'Kohen Gadol nichnas sgan u-meshammesh tachtav.
Because so that he'd be ready to go ahead and, you know,
like I said, he's the vice president, he's ready if something happens
to the כהן גדול. So the גמרא Gemara infers from this, it's
a pretty big stretch, but it infers from this that that's the
only thing the סגן did. So clearly, if the סגן had a
function of actually drawing a lot, then he wouldn't have said that
that's the only function of the סגן. So it becomes quite interesting
that רבי חנניא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Hanania Sgan HaKohanim is the one
that's downplaying the role of the סגן. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Now we've been shifting to a lot of אגדתא, aggadata, we shift
again to some אגדתא, aggadata, let's take a look. ארבעים שנה ששימש
שמעון הצדיק היה גורל עולה בימין.
Arba'im shana she-shimmesh Shimon HaTzadik haya
goral oleh b'yamin. The entire 40 years, and this goes back though
to your point about the idea that גורל goral is not chance,
but about sort of says something about God's sort of involvement. So
for the 40 years that שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik was the כהן
גדול, because you know he was righteous and the generation was righteous,
so it always was the good סימן. siman. The one that said
להשם always came up in the right hand. מכאן ואילך Mi-kan va-eilach
after שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik and we know that's when you had
a big major revolving door of כהנים גדולים, Kohanim Gedolim, so מכאן
ואילך פעמים עולה בימין פעמים עולה בשמאל. mi-kan va-eilach p'amim oleh b'yamin
p'amim oleh b'smol. It was random, sometimes right, sometimes left, or maybe
not random, maybe only for the good כהנים, Kohanim, but anyway clearly
things were not at the same level. והיה לשון של זהורית מלבין.
V'haya lashon shel zehorit malbin. But at least the one saving grace
was that the red string would turn white. So even in the
days of שמעון הצדיק? Shimon HaTzadik? No, no, no, meaning even after
שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik you still had the red string turning white.
You didn't have everything was you know the sense of God's full
favor of the people was not there, you didn't have this always
going up
in the right hand, but you still had the sense of
the sins were atoned, the
red string would turn white. מכאן ואילך, Mi-kan va-eilach, after that period,
it doesn't tell us a number of years. It was interesting שמעון
הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik going back and forth? שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik here?
No, no, no, we're talking about the ירידת הדורות. yeridat ha-dorot. As
the generations progressed after שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik, more and more symbols
of God's sort of withdrawing God's presence or God's withdrawing no, withdrawing
God's favor, you kept on losing more and more things that indicated
God's favor. But it didn't say where the מכאן ואילך mi-kan va-eilach
is though, I mean so far. Yeah, in the next generation whatever
that time was, מכאן ואילך פעמים מלבין פעמים אינו מלבין. mi-kan va-eilach
p'amim malbin p'amim eino malbin. Sometimes the string would turn red, sometimes
not. When you're now three generations removed from שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik,
you're losing the symbolism of the string turning white. But you still
had the symbolism even at that third generation: והיה נר מערבי דולק.
V'haya ner ma'aravi dolek. The western light of the מנורה, Menorah, right?
was still it was burning, this was the idea that you started
lighting the מנורה Menorah with the western light.
Is the גמרא Gemara always contrasting this to שמעון הצדיק? Shimon HaTzadik?
שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik versus the other, at least that's the way
I see it.
How do they oh, you
know, שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik then מכאן ואילך, mi-kan va-eilach, when שמעון
הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik and מכאן ואילך, mi-kan va-eilach, it's going back and
forth.
Oh, והיה לשון של זהורית מלבין V'haya lashon shel zehorit malbin was
in the time of שמעון הצדיק.
Shimon HaTzadik. Huh, after it's מכאן ואילך.
mi-kan va-eilach. That's interesting.
It's because of the repetition of the refrain of מכאן ואילך. mi-kan
va-eilach.
All right, I hear that, that wasn't the way huh, I was
trying maybe to read a little bit more a little bit more
sympathetic that things were going down in a slower progression.
One minute.
Yeah, you're right, I mean if you look at רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu
Chananel, if you look at
רבינו חננאל... Rabbeinu Chananel... מם שנה ששימש שמעון הצדיק היה גורל עולה
בימין ובלשון זהורית מלבין והייתה נר מערבי דולק והייתה אש המערכה מתגברת
והייתה ברכה בעומר ובשתי הלחם. Mem shanah sheshimesh Shimon haTzadik haya goral
oleh biyamin uvelashon zehorit malbin vehayta ner ma'aravi dolek vehayta esh hama'aracha
mitgaberet vehayta bracha ba'omer uvishtei halechem. Okay, so I stand corrected. I
was trying to read it at a much more slow, you know,
gradual decline, but so much for my reading. Okay. So much for
your character. So much for my, exactly. Let's go back and read
it now the correct way. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ארבעים שנה Arba'im
shanah let's do it again from the top. ששימש שמעון הצדיק היה
גורל עולה בימין. sheshimesh Shimon haTzadik haya goral oleh biyamin. מכאן ואילך
mikan va'eilach פעמים עולה בימין פעמים עולה בשמאל. p'amim oleh biyamin p'amim
oleh bismol. So during the time of שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik it
was always in the right, after שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik time, sometimes
right, sometimes left. ולשון של זהורית מלבין velashon shel zehorit malbin and
in the time of שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik the red string would
always turn white. מכאן ואילך mikan va'eilach after שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik
time, פעמים מלבין פעמים אינו מלבין, p'amim malbin p'amim eino malbin, sometimes
it turned white, sometimes not. ונר מערבי דולק vener ma'aravi dolek in
the time of שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik the western light of the
מנורה menorah was always still lit, which means what? They would light
it first in the lighting of the מנורה, menorah, the one that
pointed towards the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, whether it was the middle
stem or whether it was the second one in from the east.
Anyway, they started lighting with it and then the other ones burnt
out before it. So it was considered a constant נס nes that
this one was always lit first and always lasted the longest. מכאן
ואילך mikan va'eilach after that period, פעמים דולק פעמים כבה. p'amim dolek
p'amim kaveh. Sometimes it would light the whole, you know, longer than
the others, sometimes it would be extinguished. ואש המערכה מתגברת ve'esh hama'aracha
mitgaberet so מתגבר mitgaber
in the time of שמעון הצדיק Shimon haTzadik the fire on the
top of the מזבח mizbeiach would always sort of be powerful even
without being fed fuel. ולא היו כהנים צריכים להביא עצים למערכה velo
hayu kohanim tzrichim lehavi eitzim lama'aracha the כהנים kohanim would not have
to bring extra wood to feed the fire חוץ משני גזירי עצים
כדי לקיים מצות עצים. chutz mishnei gezeirei eitzim kedei lekayeim mitzvat eitzim.
The only thing they would bring is the two, you know, logs
of the wood which we discussed before,
because there was a מצוה mitzvah to add wood, but practically you
did not need to feed the fire. מכאן ואילך mikan va'eilach after
the time of שמעון הצדיק, Shimon haTzadik, פעמים מתגבר פעמים אין מתגבר
p'amim mitgaber p'amim ein mitgaber sometimes it would sort of have it,
you know, be strong on its own and sometimes it wouldn't be
strong on its own and you would really need to feed it
fuel, feed it wood. ולא היו כהנים נמנעים מלהביא עצים למערכה כל
היום כולו velo hayu kohanim nimna'im melehavi eitzim lama'aracha kol hayom kulo
they would have to feed the fire the entire day constantly feeding
it wood. ונשתלחה ברכה בעומר ובשתי הלחם ובלחם הפנים. venishtalecha bracha ba'omer
uvishtei halechem uvlechem hapanim. Now in the time again of שמעון הצדיק
Shimon haTzadik there was a blessing in the bread, you know, given
from heaven in the bread, whether it was the עומר omer or
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on שבועות Shavuos or the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim every שבת. Shabbos. וכל כהן שמגיע כזית vechol kohen shemagi'a
kezayis and every כהן if you just got a כזית, kezayis, יש
אוכלו ושבע ויש אוכלו ומותיר. yesh ochlo vesavei'a veyesh ochlo umosir. Either
you would eat a כזית kezayis and you'd be totally satisfied or
you'd eat it and you'd even have leftovers. This was the blessing
in the bread in the time of שמעון הצדיק. Shimon haTzadik. מכאן
ואילך mikan va'eilach afterwards, נשתלחה מאירה בעומר ובשתי הלחם ובלחם הפנים, nishtalecha
me'eira ba'omer uvishtei halechem uvlechem hapanim, rather than a blessing being sent
down into them, a curse was sent down into it. וכל כהן
מגיעו כפול vechol kohen magi'o kefol which is by the way, you
know, this is even מאירה me'eira is even worse, like until now
it was like the withdrawal of something miraculous. Here we're talking about,
you know, actually something bad being sent down, you know, in terms
of the contrast. And every כהן would not get a כזית, kezayis,
they would get כפול kefol like a lentil bean.
הצנועין מושכין את ידיהן hatznu'in moshchin et yedeihen so the more private
ones, the less, you know, aggressive ones, they would just, you know,
withdraw their hands. They would say, I'm not, you know, I don't
want any.
והגרגרנים נוטלין ואוכלין vehagarganim notlin ve'ochlin
and the voracious ones, נוטלין ואוכלין notlin ve'ochlin they would sort of
just, they would grab and they would eat. ומעשה באחד שנטל חלקו
וחלק חבירו uma'aseh be'echad shenatal chelko vechelek chaveiro somebody grabbed his portion
and his friend's portion, והיו קוראים אותו בן חמצן vehayu kor'im oto
ben hamtzan and they called him the son of the thief or
we'll see what חמצן hamtzan means in a minute. Just one comment
before we turn the page which is first of all the מהרש''א
Maharsha says that there's a double significance here that if you get
a כזית kezayis he sort of says a כזית kezayis is fit
for ברכה. bracha. ואכלת ושבעת, veachalta vesavata, you know, ואכלת veachalta is
כזית kezayis ושבעת vesavata is the next level. We make a ברכת
המזון birkat hamazon on just a כזית. kezayis. So a כזית kezayis
though is somehow can is fit to receive the blessing to give
you שביעה. sevi'ah. Less than a כזית, kezayis, that's why he reads
the first step here was not just that it didn't give you
satisfaction but that the amount that each person got was less than
a כזית kezayis and wasn't even fit for שביעה. sevi'ah. The other
important things to sort of mention here is I wanted to just
show you this short little תוספות, Tosafot, very cute תוספות. Tosafot. וקראו
אותו חמצן כל ימיו vekara'u oto hamtzan kol yamav they called him
חמצן hamtzan here it was I suppose בן חמצן. ben hamtzan. So
תוספות Tosafot says אף על פי שגם הגרגרנים אחרים חוטפים ואוכלים. af
al pi shegam hagarganim acherim chotfim ve'ochlin. Everybody, all of the people
that were not הצנועים. hatznu'im. The little תוספות Tosafot on ל''ט עמוד
א', lamed tet amud aleph, טרף בקלפי. taraf bakalpi. Okay,
it has a confusing דיבור המתחיל. dibbur hamatchil. Yeah, it
does. Okay. So he says אף על פי שגם הגרגרנים אחרים חוטפים
ואוכלים af al pi shegam hagarganim acherim chotfim ve'ochlin everybody was grabbing
I mean other than הצנועים. hatznu'im. So why did this guy get
labeled חמצן? hamtzan? So כמותו, kemoto, האי דקראו לו חמצן טפי מאחריני
יש לומר לפי שהוא חטף מחמצן אחר. hai dekara'u lo hamtzan tefei
me'achrinei yesh lomar lefi shehu chataf mehamtzan acher.
This guy was such a, you know, was so aggressive that it's
one thing to steal from the communal pot to like jump in
and grab from the communal pot fast and push people aside. It's
another thing to grab off of somebody else's plate. אינמי, Inami, אחרים
לא הקפידו כשחיו חוטפים זה מזה. acherim lo hikpidu kshehayu chotfin zeh
mizeh. אבל זה כשזה חטף מידו הקפיד. Aval zeh kshezeh chataf miyado
hikpid. This is a less interesting answer. The guy didn't like it
when he was, he had his food grabbed, but I like the
idea that he was so aggressive, he not, you know, it wasn't
enough to grab from the communal station. But anyway, but some people
figured look, we're not gonna get a ברכה, bracha, it's only a
small amount. Now, by the way, I have to tell you that
it's interesting because you wouldn't think necessarily that the most appropriate thing
is not to take a portion of the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim.
You would think it's a מצוה mitzvah to eat from it. So
I only get a פול מצרי, pul Mitzri, you know? So big
deal, it's a מצוה. mitzvah. I'm not doing it to fill myself
up. So, you know, it's sort of like this interesting concept like
good guys versus bad guys where you would imagine the best thing
to do would be to take what you got and be happy.
Exactly. Not to withdraw and not to...
wait, is there a מצוה mitzvah to eat from the לחם הפנים?
Lechem HaPanim? Well, again, it's not like it's an individual מצוה mitzvah
for a כהן to do it. It's not like he's מבטל מצוה.
mevatel mitzvah. But the idea that, you know, that this is from
the, you know, from שולחן השם Shulchan Hashem and...
did you say something about תרומה Terumah for example? No, I mentioned
תרומה. Terumah. This is what the כהנים Kohanim eat.
Yeah, I mean, it's in
the same sort of מצוה.
mitzvah. I, Daniel, did you want to say something?
You had a question on the story. So they said at the
time when the כהן גדול gets it and... but I was just
looking at that we're not supposed to rely on a סימן. siman.
Yeah, so it gets to the larger whole issue exactly that about
the, you know, we do have these symbols of which is what
this whole story was symbols of God's presence in the מקדש. Mikdash.
נר מערבי, Ner Ma'aravi, לשון של זהורית Lashon Shel Zehoris and it
does get to the whole issue about the drawing of the lots
altogether, what it symbolizes. So let's leave that question to bother us
for a while and I'm going to see if I can find
more on that.
לשון של זהורית Lashon Shel Zehoris turned white.
We'll talk about that. No, when it gets pushed over. Yeah, but
we'll talk about that. Okay, so let's keep on going with the
גמרא. אמר רבה בר בר שילא: Amar Rabba Bar Bar Shila: מאי
קרא? Mai Kra? Where's the פסוק pasuk that you see חמצן Chamtzen
means this bad thing like a thief? So אלהי פלטני מיד רשע,
Elokei paltseini miyad rasha, God save me from the hand of the
wicked person, מכף מעול וחומץ. mikaf me'avel vechometz. From the hand of
the perverter and the חומץ. chometz. So clearly it's not something good.
I don't know if we know that, you know, one who does
injustice, I'm not sure it would necessarily mean steal. רבא אמר מהכא:
Rava amar meihacha: למדו היטב דרשו משפט, limdu heiteiv dirshu mishpat, learn
well, seek out justice, אשרו חמוץ. ashru chamotz. You know, strengthen the
one who has been oppressed or
so again, or according to this, stolen from. So clearly this is,
so clearly חמוץ chamotz means to do some violence, to do some
against the person. אשרו חמוץ ולא אשרו חומץ. Ashru chamotz velo ashru
chometz. And they're sort of saying the obvious point, strengthen the one
who has been injured, who has had this violence or theft done
against them and not the one that is actually doing it. Now
רש"י Rashi, says that's obvious and a little redundant and he says
it's actually more relevant to a דרשה drasha they make in סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, which is what... חומץ? chometz? Yeah, it's an interesting question about
חומץ chometz and חמס chamas and... I don't know, that's a good
point. I didn't think about the חמס chamas and the
חומץ, chometz, certainly.
Yeah, you can foment
violence.
Foment. Alright, moving on, moving on. Were you guys just unruly when
I wasn't here? אשרו חמוץ... Ashru chamotz... okay.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: אותה שנה שמת בה שמעון
הצדיק, Osa shana shemeis bah Shimon HaTzadik, the year that Shimon HaTzadik
died, אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them: בשנה זו הוא
מת, Beshana zo hu meis, this year he, meaning I, speaking about
myself in the third person, he will die. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
the people said to him: מניין אתה יודע? Minyin ata yodeia? How
do you know this? אמר להם: Amar lahem: בכל יום הכיפורים היה
מזדמן לי זקן אחד, Bechol Yom HaKippurim haya mizdamen li zaken echad,
every Yom Kippur when I would go into the קודש קודשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, an elder person would be there, לבוש לבנים ועטוף לבנים, lavush
levanim ve'atuf levanim, dressed in white and wrapped in white. נכנס עמי
ויצא עמי. Nichnas imi veyatza imi. He would go in with me
and come out with me.
והיום נזדמן לי זקן אחד לבוש שחורים ועטוף שחורים. Vehayom nizdamen li
zaken echad lavush shechorim ve'atuf shechorim. And this time he was this
elder was dressed in black and wrapped in black. נכנס עמי ולא
יצא עמי. Nichnas imi velo yatza imi. He went in with me
and he didn't go out with me.
So obviously it's a symbol that I'm going to die and I'm
not going to, right, I'm not going to see out the year.
אחר הרגל חלה שבעה ימים, Achar haregel chala shiva yamim, so he
must have said this pretty soon after Yom Kippur because after the
רגל, regel, after סוכות, Succos, he was sick for seven days ומת
umeis and he died.
And then we, you prepare.
That's an interesting point, right? Seven day parallel. ונמנעו אחיו הכהנים לברך
בשם. Venimneu echav hakohanim levareich bashem. And his, and after that, and
we didn't mention this before in the things that stopped after the
time of Shimon HaTzadik, his fellow כהנים Kohanim no longer said God's
name explicitly because they felt they weren't at the level that they
were fit to do it. The later כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim after
Shimon HaTzadik...
so when did they not say it, I mean, on Yom Kippur?
Or no, they would do it anyway during normal ברכת כהנים Birchas
Kohanim and whatnot. But in general, any ברכה bracha in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash would be with שם המפורש. Shem HaMiforash And
after Shimon HaTzadik they felt they were not at the level and
they did not do it. I do want to say by the
way that there's an interesting ירושלמי Yerushalmi that asks about this whole...
story about the person going in with him, which basically says, what
do you mean? It says וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד בבואו
אל הקדש. vechol adam lo yihyeh be'ohel moed be'vo'o el hakodesh. So
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said, right, this isn't an אדם, adam, this is
a
מלאך. malach. So alright, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
says like
this, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Rashi says it was that they did not say them in ברכת
כהנים Birchas Kohanim that they did not say them בשם המפורש.
beshem hamiforash. Right, that's what I said, ברכת כהנים. Birchas Kohanim.
Oh, but you said they didn't say בשם חטאת beshem chattas but
בשם המפורש.
beshem hamiforash. I either, but even... meaning הכהנים ha-kohanim he's talking about
the fact because it's in the plural. Right? It's not just later
כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim. הכהנים ha-kohanim means he talks on a regular
basis, but whenever ברכה bracha in the מקדש Mikdash would be בשם
beshem and בשם המפורש.
beshem
hamiforash. So he was around that considered themselves...
Oh, that's a good point. Right, because it wasn't just him that
was doing it when he was around. I guess you see that
from the previous discussion that the whole דור dor was considered to
be at a higher level, so his presence, you know, allowed everybody
to be מברך בשם. mevarech beshem. But yeah, that's a very good
point.
I would have understood it meaning more like that they were mourning
or something...
Oh, you mean just for that period?
Yes, I would have thought that by רש"י, Rashi right?
Yeah, but נמנעו... nimne'u... but the language of
נמנעו מלברך בשם nimne'u milivarech beshem does not sound like an ongoing
thing.
Look, I can take a look, like the side note here is
pointing to תוספות Tosafos in סוטה, Sotah, so I'd have to look
that up. But I don't... so maybe there are other explanations about
that, but I think רש"י Rashi is reflecting the sense that it
means נמנעו nimne'u sounds like an ongoing thing. I mean, yeah, the
רבי עקיבא איגר Rebbi Akiva Eiger points to the תוספות. Tosafos. What?
There was a note here at the bottom from
someone... לפי שהכירו מפני קדושת השם, lefi she-hikiru mipnei kedushas HaShem, they
were afraid.
Yeah, how רש"י says ודא שמעון הצדיק הוי כדאי... ve-da Shimon HaTzadik
havay kedai...
Yeah, but I think the point was a good one. They were
the same כהנים, Kohanim, but somehow his absence made them all אינו
כדאי. eino kedai. So that's also an interesting thing. Give me one
second here, just see if I can find it very quickly.
That makes sense to me that they were כדאי kedai when he
was...
in his presence.
Hold on, I'm just seeing quickly if I can find this
since I have everything on my iPhone.
What דף daf does it say here? ל"ח ע"מ א'. Lamed Ches
Amud Aleph.
Hold on,
amazing the
technology works a little faster.
Okay, so what's it say? See תוספות הר"י. Tosafos ha-Ri. Let's take
a look.
So it says like this: והיינו
דקתני בספרי בכל מקום אשר אני נגלה שם תזכיר שמי ונראה דמזה
טעמא נמנעו כהנים מלברך בשם המיוחד משמת שמעון הצדיק
לפי שלא זכו שוב לגילוי שכינה. v'hainu de-katni be-Sifrei be-chol makom asher
ani nigla sham tazkir shemi ve-nir'eh de-mizeh ta'ama nimne'u Kohanim mi-livarech ba-Shem
HaMeyuchad mi-she-mes Shimon HaTzadik lefi she-lo zachu shuv le-giluy Shechina. So he
says that because of... so that's interesting. תוספות Tosafos basically ties it
into into not the כהנים Kohanim were unfit, but everything we've seen
here which were symbols of lack of God's full presence. So he
says the ability to say שם המפורש required the full presence of
the שכינה, Shechina, the full גילוי שכינה. giluy Shechina. So that's an
interesting alternate explanation. Okay, let's keep on going.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this. תנו רבנן ארבעים שנה קודם
חורבן הבית. Tanu Rabbanan Arba'im shana kodem churban ha-Bayis. So for the
forty years before the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, was destroyed, לא היה
גורל עולה בימין. lo hayah goral oleh be-yamin. So as opposed to
the period after שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik where sometimes it was right,
sometimes it was left, in the forty years leading...
What was the relation to
the chronology of the בית שני?
Beis Sheni? Hundred some odd years, I don't know the exact.
שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik was the second century before the Common Era.
So, okay, so in the last forty years, in the last forty
years, it would never come up in the right, it would always
be in the left, which is obviously, you know, a very negative
symbol. ולא היה לשון של זהורית מלבין v'lo hayah lashon shel zehoris
malbin and again, as opposed to before where sometimes it would be
white and sometimes red, here it was never, it never turned white.
ולא היה נר מערבי דולק v'lo hayah ner ma'aravi dolek and as
opposed to before where sometimes after שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik it would
last more than the other lights, here it would never last more
than the other lights. והיו דלתות היכל נפתחות מאליהן. ve-hayu daltos Heichal
niftachos me-aleihen. The doors of the היכל Heichal would just open up
on their own. They wouldn't need to be opened. Yeah, but it
basically was sort of like welcoming the enemies to come in. עד
שגער בהן רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. ad she-ga'ar ba-hen Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai. So רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai yelled at
them. אמר לו amar lo and he said to it: היכל היכל
מפני מה אתה מבעית את עצמך? Heichal Heichal mipnei mah attah mave'is
es atzmecha? Why are you, you know, disturbing yourself, confusing yourself, meaning
you know, why are you so eager to make this happen? יודע
אני בך שסופך עתיד ליחרב. yode'a ani becha she-sofcha asid liyocharev. You
know, you don't need to send me any more signs. I know
you're going to be destroyed. וכבר נתנבא עליך זכריה בן עדו U'chevar
nitnaba alecha Zecharia ben Iddo and Zecharia ben Iddo has already prophesied
about you,
פתח לבנון דלתיך. Ptach Levanon dlatecha. לבנון, Levanon, which often is understood
to mean the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash open up your doors. ותאכל
אש בארזיך V'tochal esh b'arozecha and the fire will consume in your
cedar trees. So this is the opening up, it opens up its
own doors to invite in the enemy. אמר רבי יצחק בן טבלאי,
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak ben Tablai, למה נקרא שמו לבנון? Lama nikra shemo
Levanon? Why was the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. called
לבנון? Levanon? שמלבין עונותיהן של ישראל Shemalbin avonoteihem shel Yisrael because it
would again, sort of like the red string, it would whiten their
sins. אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה, Amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia, למה
נקרא שמו יער? Lama nikra shemo Yaar? Why is it called a
forest? דכתיב, Dechtiv, בית יער הלבנון, Beit Yaar HaLevanon, the house of
the forest of Lebanon. So לבנון, Levanon, if לבנון Levanon means the
מקדש, Mikdash, why is it called a forest? לומר לך, Lomar lecha,
to tell you, מה יער מלבלב, Ma yaar melavlev, the same way
a forest blossoms, אף בית המקדש מלבלב, Af Beit HaMikdash melavlev, it
would happen in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash? דאמר רב הושעיא בשעה
שבנה שלמה בית המקדש, De'amar Rav Hoshaia b'shaa shebana Shlomo Beit HaMikdash,
נטע בו
כל מיני מגדים של זהב. Nata bo kol minei megadim shel zahav.
He would, he planted all delicacies of
gold. והיו מוציאין פירות בזמניהן V'hayu motzi'in peirot bizmaneihem and fruit would
come out in their right time. The Maharsha claims that the fruit
here is golden fruit.
So it was real trees,
but it's out of gold. וכיון שהרוח מנשבת בהן, V'keivan sheharuach menashevet
bahen, when the wind would blow them, היו נושרין פירותיהן, Hayu noshrin
peiroteihem, they would drop their fruit. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ירעש כלבנון פריו, Yiraash
kaLevanon piryo, and it would
make noise
like the לבנון, Levanon, its fruit. ומהן היתה פרנסה לכהונה U'mehen hayita
parnasa l'kehuna and from there the כהנים kohanim would be able to
support themselves, according to, especially if they were gold. Golden fruit on
trees in the בית המקדש? I don't know. Well, so they were
gold, they weren't real fruit.
What's that midrash of the golden apple?
Yeah, exactly. וכיון
שנכנסו עובדי כוכבים להיכל,
V'keivan shenichnasu
ovdei kochavim l'heichal, and when the enemies entered into the היכל, Heichal,
יבשו, Yaveshu, they dried up, they withered. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ופרח לבנון אמלל,
U'ferach Levanon umlal, and the blossom of the לבנון Levanon will become,
you know, bereaved. ועתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחזירה לנו, V'atid HaKadosh Baruch
Hu l'hachzira lanu, and in the end return it to us. שנאמר,
Shene'emar, פרח תפרח ותגל אף גילת ורנן כבוד הלבנון נתן לה. Paroch
tifrach v'tagel af gilat v'ranen kevod haLevanon nutan lah. So it should
blossom forth and rejoice and sing forth because the glory of the
לבנון Levanon will be given to us, which is a nice way
to end, since we were all talking about how things went to
pot right after שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzaddik, now we end with this
nice idea that eventually it will come back. Okay, now we return
to some of the more halakhic discussion about the עבודה. Let's take
a look. נתן עליהן שני שעירין, Natan aleihen shenei se'irin,
he put the two lots on the two goats. תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabanan, עשר פעמים מזכיר כהן גדול את השם בו ביום. Eser peamim
mazkir Kohen Gadol et HaShem bo bayom. Ten times the כהן גדול
mentions God's explicit name on יום כיפור. ג' בוידוי ראשון, Gimel b'vidui
rishon, three in the first וידוי, vidui, right? אנא השם כפר
נא לעונות. Ana HaShem kaper na l'avonot. Here Rashi quotes it. What
is it?
אנא
השם חטאתי, Ana HaShem chatati, אנא השם כפר נא, Ana HaShem kaper
na, and then לפני השם תטהרו. Lifnei HaShem titharu. Okay, so each
וידוי vidui would have three times of saying God's name. And, so
three times three, and there'd be three וידויים. viduiim.
What? Way near the top. Okay.
ג' בוידוי ראשון, Gimel b'vidui rishon, three in the first וידוי, vidui,
right? אנא
השם, Ana HaShem, okay, אנא השם
כפר נא, Ana HaShem kaper na, חטאתי, Chatati, אנא השם כפר, Ana
HaShem kaper, and לפני השם תטהרו. Lifnei HaShem titharu. וג' בוידוי שני,
V'gimel b'vidui sheni, three again in the second וידוי vidui which was
on his part for now for the כהנים. kohanim. וג' בשעיר המשתלח,
V'gimel b'se'ir hamishtaleiach, three for the שעיר se'ir that would be sent
off the cliff. That's nine. ואחד בגורלות, V'echad b'goralot, and one when
he says for the גורלות, goralot, he said להשם or להשם חטאת.
Okay, so ten times. וכבר אמר השם, U'chevar amar HaShem, and when
he said God's name, ונשמע קולו ביריחו, V'nishma kulo b'Yiricho, it could
already be heard all the way in יריחו. Yiricho. He would say
it so loud. אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabba bar bar
Chana, מירושלים ליריחו עשר פרסאות. MiYerushalayim l'Yiricho eser parsaot. From ירושלים Yerushalayim
to יריחו Yiricho is ten פרסאות. parsaot. A פרסה parsa is four
מיל, mil, which is eight thousand אמה, amah, which is about twelve
thousand feet, which is what, like two miles? So this is about
twenty miles. Is that how far it is from ירושלים Yerushalayim to
יריחו, Yiricho, twenty miles give or take? Somebody will look it up.
וציר דלתות ההיכל נשמע בשמונה תחומי שבת. V'tzir daltot haHeichal nishma b'shmona
techumei Shabbat. When they would open the היכל, Heichal, the hearing, the
creaking of the hinges of the doors of the היכל Heichal could
be heard within eight תחום שבת. techum Shabbat. So תחום שבת techum
Shabbat
is two thousand אמות, amot, sixteen thousand אמות.
amot. Okay, that's a lot less, that's only two פרסה. parsa. But
anyway,
עזים שביריחו, Izim sheb'Yiricho, the goats all the way in יריחו, Yiricho,
היו מתעטשות מריח הקטורת. Hayu mitatshot mereiach haktoret. They would pass gas
because of the smell of the incense that would get all the
way, sneeze, I'm sorry, sneeze, right? This עיטושא מהא לעיטושא מהתא, itusha
meha l'itusha mehata, but you're probably right, it's probably sneezing. Okay, it
would sneeze because
of the smell of the קטורת ktoret that would reach all the
way to יריחו. Yiricho. נשים שביריחו, Nashim sheb'Yiricho, אינן צריכין להתבשם מריח
קטורת. Einan tzerichin l'hitbasem mereiach ktoret. The women in יריחו Yiricho would
not have to use perfume because they would naturally come on them
from the קטורת. ktoret.
That's far away from the, you know, we said before that they
didn't, the
fumigation of בית אבטינס.
Beit Abtinas. putting on her jewelry or her perfume and stuff like
jewelry because of the קטורת *ketoret*. Now, why in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*? We
were talking about יריחו *Yericho*. So the—so I sort of guessed—thought as
I was learning this and then I saw the מהרשא *Maharsha* said
it. He says, a כלה *kala* needs a lot more—would assume a
lot more perfume than a normal woman, so therefore in יריחו *Yericho*
the normal amount of perfume that would be good for the women
in יריחו *Yericho*, but for the כלה *kala* only the כלות *kalot*
in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* had enough that they would normally want and that
that could serve as a substitute.
What does that mean for the כהנים *kohanim*?
Overpowering? Yeah, well, that's a good point too. Now תוספות *Tosafos* by
the way also asks, what about the fact that you're not allowed
to benefit from the smell of the קטורת *ketoret*? So—so תוספות *Tosafos*
writes it was you didn't do it in any active way, it
was all very passive. If you look at the last line of
תוספות *Tosafos* כלה שבירושלים *kala shebe-Yerushalayim* he says, אינו אסור אלא שלא
יקרבו עצמן לזה כדי להריח יותר *aino assur ela shelo yikrevu atzman
lizeh kedei leharicha yoter*. But if it happened completely passively, it would
not be an issue.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר רבי יוסי בן
דוגלא *Amar Rabbi Yosi ben Dugla*—I'm not sure how you say it—עזים
היו לאבא בהרי מכמר *izim hayu leabba beharai michmar*, my father had
goats, שהיו מתעטשות מריח הקטורת *shehayu mitatshot mereiach haktoret* and they would
sneeze because of the smell of the קטורת *ketoret*. Where is הרי
מכמר *Harai Michmar*? I have no idea. אמר רבי חייא בר אבין
אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Avin Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha*: סח לי זקן אחד *sach li zaken echad*, an
elder person once whispered to me, פעם אחת הלכתי לשילה *paam achat
halachti le-Shilo*, I went to שילה *Shilo*, where the—you know where it
used to be where the משכן *Mishkan* was, ורחתי ריח קטורת מבין
כתליה *v'reiachti reiach ketoret mibein kotleha*, and the smell of the קטורת
*ketoret* now not coming from the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* from when
the משכן *Mishkan* was in שילה *Shilo* was still present between the
cracks of the wall. אמר רבי ינאי *Amar Rabbi Yannai*. Now, okay,
done with that. Now back to the discussion of the עבודה *Avodah*.
אמר רבי ינאי עליית גורל goral מתוך קלפי מעכבת *Amar Rabbi Yannai
aliyat goral mitoch kalfi meakevet*. Taking the גורל goral. *goral* from the
box is, you know, that is מעכב *meakev*, prevents it from being
good. If you just called the name or you just—you just arbitrarily
assigned them, it would not be good. You have to actually draw
it from the box. הנחה אינה מעכבת *hanacha eina meakevet*, but the
placing on the top of the animal that does not prevent you
from being יוצא yotzei, *yotze*.
What does it mean עליית גורל *aliyat goral*, does that mean taking
it out?
Taking it out. Yeah, doing this act of drawing the random lot,
if you don't do that then you can't go forward, then you
can't call this one לשם *La-Shem* and this one לעזאזל *La-Azazel* by
naming it, by arbitrarily assigning it. You have to do the drawing
of the lot. If you don't do it, you can't move forward.
This is what I said, it might not be an עבודה *Avodah*
but it might still be מעכב *meakev*.
אמר עליית גורל מתוך קלפי מעכבת *Amar aliyat goral mitoch kalfi meakevet*
means if you don't do it.
If you don't do it. It prevents—right, the non-doing of it is
מעכב *meakev*, correct.
ורבי יוחנן אמר אף עלייה אינה
מעכבת *V'Rabbi Yochanan amar af aliya eina meakevet*. No, even if you
don't do it, maybe you just say לשם חטאת *La-Shem Chatas*, even
if you don't do the drawing, בדיעבד *b'diavad* it's okay. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אליבא דרבי יהודה Aliba d'Reb Yehuda, דאמר
דברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבחוץ לא מעכבא *Aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar devarim
ha-naasim b'vigdei lavan mibachutz lo meakva*. So we are going to see
later that there's a debate between רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
and רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia*, which is, anything that is done בחוץ
*bachutz*—now בחוץ *bachutz* in this context is very—is very deceptive, because בחוץ
*bachutz* in this context means anything outside the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim*.
Anything in the היכל *Heichal* and—and in the larger עזרה *Azarah*. So
רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* says, if you mix up the
order of things that are נעשים *naasim* in the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh
HaKodashim*, but anything else, if you go out of order, בדיעבד *b'diavad*
it's okay. רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia* says no, בדיעבד *b'diavad* it's not
good if you go out of order. And the גמרא *Gemara* is
going to assume that the same debate of whether order is מעכב
*meakev* might translate into whether doing the act itself is מעכב *meakev*.
So let's take a look. Okay, we'll read this line and just
that's what we'll wrap up for today. אליבא דרבי יהודה דאמר *Aliba
d'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar*, according to רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says,
דברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבחוץ לא מעכבא *devarim ha-naasim b'vigdei lavan mibachutz
lo meakva*, things when the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* wears the בגדי
לבן *bigdei lavan* out of the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim*, the order
isn't מעכב *meakev*, and the גמרא *Gemara* therefore assumes that means that
doing it won't be מעכב *meakev*. כולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא מעכבא
*Kuli alma lo pligi delo meakva*, nobody would disagree that this would
not be a—this would not prevent it from being good. This is
done outside in בגדי לבן *bigdei lavan*, so it's therefore it's not
מעכב *meakev*. כי פליגי Ki peligi, *Ki pligi*, when do they debate?
אליבא דרבי נחמיה *Aliba d'Rabbi Nechemia*, according to רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia*
who normally says that order is מעכב *meakev*, even outside the קודש
הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim*. מאן דאמר מעכבא *Man d'amar meakva*, so the one
that says that drawing the lot is מעכב *meakev*, כרבי נחמיה *k'Rabbi
Nechemia*, that's like רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia*, that makes sense. ומאן דאמר
לא מעכבא *Uman d'amar lo meakva*, the other one that says it
does not prevent you from being יוצא yotzei *yotze*, הני מילי *hani
milei* עבודה *avodah*, when—when does רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia* say that order
matters or doing it matters and if you don't do it you're
not יוצא yotzei, *yotze*, that's a real עבודה *avodah*. הגרלה hagrala. לאו
עבודה היא *Hagralah lav avodah hi*, the drawing of the lot is
not עבודה *avodah* and this ties back to what I said because
it could be done with the left hand, it could be done
with a non כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. So this might not be
מעכב *meakev* even according to רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Nechemia* who normally is
more strict. One more line about a possible even—even like more extreme
reading of this debate. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, some say, אליבא דרבי
נחמיה דאמר מעכבא כולי עלמא לא פליגי *aliba d'Rabbi Nechemia d'amar meakva
kuli alma lo pligi* No, everybody would agree that according to רב
נחמיה Reb Nechemiah who normally says order matters, he would say that
here too, if you don't, the doing it matters and if you
don't do it you're not יוצא, yotzei? even though it's not an
עבודה, even though it's just הגרלה. hagrala כי פליגי, what's the debate?
אליבא דרבי יהודה, according to רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda who normally says
that things outside are not מעכב, at least the order isn't מעכב.
מאן דאמר לא מעכבא, Man d'amar lo meakva, if you say that
the drawing lots is not prevent you from being יוצא according to
רבי יהודה, כרבי יהודה. k'Reb Yehuda. ומאן דאמר מעכבא, U'man d'amar meakva,
and the one that says that it does prevent you from being
יוצא, even according to רבי יהודה who normally gives you more latitude,
שאני הכא, shani hacha, here it's different, דתנא בי קרא, de-tana bei
k'ra, because the פסוק pasuk repeats the importance of this. The פסוק
pasuk says אשר עלה עליו הגורל אשר עלה אשר עלה, asher ala
alav hagoral, asher ala, asher ala, that the תורה Torah twice speaks
about the animal which the גורל came out on, אשר עלה אשר
עלה, asher ala, asher ala, which means is read to me, you
have to do the גורל. This must be done, including, well, not
placing it on, but including עלה עליו ala alav means raised over
it is understood, not
נתן עליו. natan alav. Yes, but it doesn't repeat it. Okay, so
what we have now is on the one hand this הגרלה is
not an עבודה, it should be done with the left, a non-כהן
גדול. Is it מעכב? The תורה Torah says you do it. Well,
there's going to be a general question about which—the תורה Torah says
do a lot of things in the עבודה—which things if you don't
do them prevent you from being יוצא? So to some degree that's
a general debate of רבי יהודה and רב נחמיה when it's out
of the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, and this might line up with
that, but to some degree this could be either more lenient or
more strict. More lenient because it's not an עבודה, so maybe everybody
would agree it's not מעכב, or more strict because the תורה Torah
repeats it twice, and therefore this, maybe more than other things, might
be מעכב. So we'll play out this debate now.